now wouldn't it be nice if there was a
formula for writing a DBQ that scored
you maximum points and that got you all
the way to Five Town well there is and
I'm about to tell you about it so if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milks let's get to it now I'm a
43-year-old bald man but I'm not too
proud to admit that in the last few
months my kids have gotten me into
fortnite and you know I kind of love it
I mean to be fair I love it but that
doesn't mean I'm any good at it because
in fact I'm pretty awful but I bring it
up because the process of getting that
juicy Victory Crown which for me is
about as rare as a New York strip on the
refrigerated Shelf at my grocery store
is similar to getting maximum points on
your DBQ which is to say there is no one
way to do it some folks drop into the
hottest spots and start mowing down
their enemies with speed and others just
camp in a bush or chill in a car until
they're forced out I'm not going to tell
you which one I am but you know don't
judge me it's my journey what I mean is
people ask me all the time a lot of the
same questions like how many paragraphs
does my DBQ need to be do I need a
conclusion paragraph do I need an intro
paragraph and on and on the answer is
that none of these things is required
for the DBQ on the national exam how
many paragraphs as many as you need what
about the conclusion paragraph no
conclusion required there's no set
format for these essay so write it in
whatever way makes sense to you you want
to drop in the middle of things with
guns blazing you do you you want to hide
in a bunker and reconsider all your
life's choices you do you but if that's
too much freedom for you and it is for a
lot of people then I'm going to give you
a formula to follow but this is
certainly not the only way to get a good
score on the DBQ but for those of you
who want some guidelines well you know
here they are and by the way I'm not
going to teach you in this video how to
write all this stuff that's what this
playlist is for right here so get your
clicky finger out if you need that kind
of help or if you want that help faster
you can check out my apsa crem course
which is linked below okay so paragraph
number one start with two or three
sentences of contextualization remember
these sentences need to contain specific
historical information and they need to
be relevant to your prompt and in that
paragraph with your thesis statement
which is your argument and miniature and
must be historically defensible now if
you've constructed your thesis properly
you're going to have established some
categories that will structure the body
paragraphs of your essay and again if
you don't know how to write such a
thesis then watch this video right here
anyway let's say you've established
three categories for your argument and
we'll call them social political and
economic and if you have three
categories in your thesis that means
you're going to have three body
paragraphs or if you have two categories
you're going to have two body paragraphs
remember your thesis is the road map for
the rest of your essay so stick to it
and you're going to be just fine okay
now moving on to the body paragraphs
here is the formula to follow you spill
the T baby topic sentence evidence
analysis but himler is not the way you
taught us to write sq's dang straight it
is but it also works beautifully in
building a DBQ paragraph so start your
paragra with a topic sentence that
summarizes everything that's about to
follow and to do this just steal it from
your thesis your thesis said for example
that some historical development change
social political and economic realities
in this time period again to be clear
that's not a passable thesis because
it's not nearly specific enough but I'm
just giving you an example okay so your
first paragraph needs to start with a
topic sentence that steals this first
category from the thesis this historical
development changed social realities
during this period so this whole
paragraph is going to be about social
change and now you need to introduce
your evidence and for a DBQ that's
that's going to be your documents and
for this example let's suppose that
documents 14 and 7 support the social
aspect of this argument so to introduce
the evidence your next sentence should
begin document 4 says and then give a
brief description of that document in
your own words not a quotation your own
words and look I can hear the collective
groans of every AP teacher in our Fair
land after hearing what I just said
documents don't talk they say don't
start a sentence with document 4 says
and look I agree it's not going to be
the most elegant historical writing ever
produced but if you're watching this
it's because you're struggling and so in
my eyes this is probably the best way to
make sure that you're actually using the
documents for evidence so you know start
your sentences however you want but this
is my recommendation if you're
struggling then you have to go one step
further and analyze the evidence that
you just mentioned and don't get freaked
out all that means is you have to show
how your evidence supports your topic
sentence which in turn is just part of
your thesis so to do this the next
sentence should begin with these words
this shows or this demonstrates and then
go on to show how your evidence proves
your argument that last part is so
important because it's the difference
between an essay that describes rbes in
an essay that argues and you'll only get
full points for arguing after you've
completed your first body paragraph then
go on and do the same thing for the
second and third body paragraphs and if
you want full points make sure that you
include at least four documents in your
analysis or if you're feeling saucy do
all seven if you want to shout at that
juicy complexity point but we're not
done yet you still have to Source at
least two documents and put in some
evidence beyond the documents and again
there's no required location for these
so maybe here in paragraph 2 I'm going
to Source One of these documents and
then Source another one in paragraph
three and what that looks like is that
right after this document I'm going to
say the events in this document are
situated in the larger context of and
that's important because and then for
this document I'm going to Source it by
saying the audience of this document was
X and that suggests and finally you need
to add in some evidence beyond the
document this needs to be specific
historical evidence that is not
mentioned in the documents it just has
to come right out of your brain fold and
you're going to handle that in the same
way that you handle the documents within
your paragraph you're going to say
another piece of evidence related to
this event is and then drop your
vocabulary and then you're going to do
the exact same thing you did with the
documents you already named it so now
explain it and then analyze it which
again means that you show me how it
proves your argument now if you follow
that format you're going to get six out
of seven points on your DBQ and the only
Point accepted here is the complexity
Point look six out of seven is a fine
score and certainly nothing to sneeze at
however given that there are about a
gazillion ways that you can earn this
complexity Point probably the most
straightforward way to earn it is to
stick to the formula I gave you and use
all seven documents to support your
argument or Source Four documents
instead of two so follow this formula
and you'll find that no matter how you
approach this essay that victory Crown
will be yours for the take okay if you
don't know how to ride a thesis then
this video is what you should watch next
and you can click here to get my apsa
Cram Course if you want me to walk you
through every point on the writing for
your course and give you some examples
of exactly how to get them all hey I'll
catch you on the flipflop I'm lur out oh
I'm the greatest fortnite player has
ever lived oh my gosh oh